Guide to The Packer Collegiate Institute records 2014.019
Brooklyn Historical Society
The Packer Collegiate Institute records
circa 1780 to 2020
Brooklyn Historical Society
Packer Collegiate Institute
Brooklyn Female Academy
2014.019
283.6 Cubic Feet in 566 boxes, one flat file drawer, and one object
314 Gigabytes in 53 video files; running time of available interviews: 16 hours, 37 minutes, and 20 seconds.
The Packer Collegiate Institute records contain administrative records, financial records, architectural records, Board of Trustees records, student and faculty records, publications, photographs, audiovisual media, event ephemera, and memorabilia, dating from circa 1780 to 2016.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Gift of The Packer Collegiate Institute, 2014. Prior to acquisition by CBH, the collection was managed by Packer's Alumni Association and its Development Office.
Historical note
The Packer Collegiate Institute was established as the Brooklyn Female Academy on Joralemon Street in the Brooklyn Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn in 1845. It was formed by a committee of local citizens who were interested in the education of young women. The school's first president was Dr. Alonzo Crittenden, who presided over a student body of 350 girls from 19 states.
The school burned down on New Years' Day, 1853, and reopened in 1854 with the assistance of a generous $65,000 gift—the largest donation to aid American secondary education at the time—from Mrs. Harriet Packer, widow of William Packer, and former trustee of the Brooklyn Female Academy. One condition of Packer's donation was her request for the dissolution of the Brooklyn Female Academy Corporation, which was to be replaced by what is today's Packer Collegiate Institute. Prominent Brooklyn architect Minard LaFever designed the Gothic Revival building, presently known as Founders Hall.
In 1883, after Crittenden's death, Truman Backus assumed the role of Packer's new president. As a result, religious studies ceased to be part of the curriculum. During this period, Packer rose to a position of national preeminence in female education. In 1887, the east wing, designed by Napoleon Le Brun, was built to house the gymnasium and science laboratories. In 1907, an Alumnae Hall was adjoined to the physical plant and the subway was constructed under Joralemon Street, which required the school to remove the observatory dome from the main building. Spanning the years 1908 to 1918, Edward Jasper Goodwin served as president and the students received letter grades for the first time.
John Denbigh succeeded Goodwin and served as president until 1938, overseeing the 1926 addition of the penthouse in Alumnae Hall. Denbigh presided over the establishment of Packer's Junior College in 1919. The school endured the financial impacts of the Great Depression, which resulted in teacher layoffs and salary cuts. In 1938 Paul Shafer became the fifth president of Packer and oversaw the Centennial celebration in 1945. During the 1950s, Packer's Junior College began awarding Associate Degrees and in 1957, Pratt Hall was added to Packer's growing complex of buildings. In 1968, President Shafer retired and Jack Skillman took over the post. In 1969, the school acquired nearby St. Ann's Church.
By 1972, the Institute experienced major changes, including the disbandment of the Junior College and the introduction of a co-ed student body. The elementary school was divided into Lower and Middle schools during this decade and Peter Esty became headmaster in 1982. Succeeding Esty was J. Geoffrey Pierson who served as the president of Packer from 1990 through 2004. Pierson oversaw the major renovation of the school's buildings and grounds, include the complete renovation of the St. Ann's Church building, which was was completed in 2003. Following Pierson's retirement, Bruce Dennis became the head of school in 2004.
Arrangement note
The records are organized into twenty-four series:
Series 1: Charters and By-laws
Series 2: Board of Trustees records
Series 3: Student administrative records
Series 4: Circulars, catalogues, and curriculum guides
Series 5: Faculty records and papers
Series 6: Administrative committees and reports
Series 7: Financial records and Annual Reports
Series 8: Student Life
Series 9: School Events
Series 10: Presidents, Headmasters, and Heads of School
Series 11: Office of Public Relations
Series 12: Development Office, Fund Raising, and Alumni records
Series 13: Yearbooks
Series 14: Architectural records
Series 15: Packer History
Series 16: Music
Series 17: Photographs
Series 18: Audio, film, and video recordings
Series 19: Instructional materials
Series 20: Junior College
Series 21: Memorabilia
Series 22: Packer family
Series 23: Miscellaneous
Series 24: Upper School History Club COVID-19 oral histories
Custodial History
Many items in the collection were donated by alumni to The Packer Collegiate Institute prior to acquisition by Brooklyn Historical Society. The identity of these donors has been noted in the finding aid whenever possible.
Scope and Contents
The Packer Collegiate Institute records contain administrative records, financial records, architectural records, correspondence, student and faculty records, publications, photographs, audiovisual media, and memorabilia, dating from circa 1780 to 2016.
The records relate to the administrative and business activities of the Institute, including meeting minutes held between the Board of Trustees and other committees, annual reports from the President of Packer to the Board of Trustees, funding raising, and alumni affairs.
Student activities are well represented in the collection. Files relating to students include student publications, yearbooks, theatrical programs, scrapbooks, student notebooks, numerous photographs, and audiovisual recordings.
Overall, the records document the history of women's education in Brooklyn, New York, and the community's rich cultural heritage.
Conditions Governing Access note
Student records and personnel files are closed to researchers for 100 years from their date of creation. All other files are open to researchers without restriction.
Born digital materials are available onsite at the Othmer Library. Requests to acess born digital materials must be made at least 2 days in advance by emailing cbhreference@bklynlibrary.org.
Related Archival Materials note
The following collections also hold material relating to The Packer Collegiate Institute:
School composition books and diaries collection (1977.348) - Contains school composition books and diaries dating from 1849 to 1901 and belonging to various Brooklyn residents, including Maggie E. Briggs (a student at The Packer Collegiate Institute).
Lillian F. Robbins certificate from the Regents of the University of the State of New York (1977.414) - Certificate issued to The Packer Collegiate Institute student in 1872.
Brooklyn schools collection (1985.054) - Includes records on over seventy Brooklyn schools, dating from 1828 to 2015.
Blackburne, Woodward, and Ottaway family papers (2013.006) - Includes the papers of Packer alumna Mary B. Woodward (1871-1943).
Henry Nagel papers (2015.004) - Includes items belong to Packer alumna Winifred Gladys Nagel Pitt, including Supplementary Reading for the Academic and Collegiate Schools booklet (1922), Class Day program (1931), the Annual Sermon to the Graduating Class (1931), clippings, photographs, and an address titled "Bender of the Twig" by school President Paul D. Schafer (1939).
Allen J. Kone collection of Brooklyn postcards (2016.014) - Contains The Packer Collegiate Institute postcards.
Jacques Cortelyou papers (ARC.025) - Includes a Report of the Treasurer of the Brooklyn Female Academy (later The Packer Collegiate Institute).
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
The majority of the materials in this collection are stored offsite and advance notice is required for use. Please contact cbhreference@bklynlibrary.org at least three weeks prior to research visit.
If digital surrogates exist, they should be used in place of the originals whenever possible.
Existence and Location of Copies
Portions of this collection have been digitized and are available on our digital collections.
Newsletters; Minutes; Hymnals; Girls' schools -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Girls -- Education -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Girls -- Education (Secondary) -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Girls -- Education (Primary) -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Financial records; Artifacts (object genre); Newspapers; Cartes-de-visite (card photographs); Brooklyn Heights (New York, N.Y.); Blueprints (reprographic copies); Black-and-white prints (photographs); Correspondence; Color prints (photographs); Children's theater -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Catalogs; Acetate film; Daguerreotypes (photographs); Education -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Education, Higher -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Architectural records; Architectural drawings (visual works); Annual reports; Administrative records; Slides (Photography); Students -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Sheet music; Single-sex schools -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Women -- Education (Higher) -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Women -- Education -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Teachers -- New York (State) -- Kings County; VHS (TM); Preparatory school students -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Preparatory schools -- Alumni and alumnae -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Photograph albums; Photographs; Schools -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Scrapbooks; Preparatory schools -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Private schools -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Yearbooks; Digital Photographs; Alumnae and alumni -- New York (State) -- Kings County; September 11 Terrorist Attacks, 2001 -- Personal narratives; Amateur theater -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Textbooks; Tintypes (prints); Alumni directories; Reports; Transcripts; Junior college students -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Packer Collegiate Institute; Packer family; Shafer, Paul D., 1902-1984; Low, Abiel Abbot, 1811-1893; Denbigh, John; Skillman, Jack, 1934-2014; Goodwin, Edward J.; Packer, Harriet L., 1820-1892; Crittenden, Alonzo, 1801-1883; Backus, Truman J. (Truman Jay), 1842-1908; Morrow, Elizabeth Post, 1896-1992
- Series 1: Charters and By-laws, 1847-2004; 1.6 Cubic Feet in four boxes
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  Scope and Contents
  The series contains charters and by-laws of the Brooklyn Female Academy (BFA) and the Packer Collegiate Institute, dating from 1847 to 2004.
  The act to incorporation and by-laws of the BFA are also included in bound volumes of the school's circulars, catalogues, and reports located in Series 4: Circulars, catalogues, and curriculum guides (boxes 509-510) and Sub-series 6.2: Administrative reports (box 507).
  - Act of Incorporation, Articles of Association and By-laws of the Brooklyn Female Academy, together with a list of Stockholders, The Trustees' Second Annual Report, Treasurer's Statement, 1847 (Box 566, Folder 10)
  - Charter and By-laws, 1896, 1922, 1940 (Box 511, Folder 2)
  - Amendments to Charter certificate, 1919 (Box 534, Folder -)
  - Charters and By-laws (13 pamphlets), 1940-1964 (Box 34, Folder -)
  - Amended Charter authorizing Packer to award AA and AAS degrees, 1941 (Box 534, Folder -)
  - Amendments to Charter certification, 2004 (Box 511, Folder 3)
- Series 2: Board of Trustees records, 1844-2000; 8.25 Cubic Feet in seventeen boxes
  The series contains records of the Board of Trustees of Packer Collegiate Institute, dating from 1844 to 2000. It is primarily composed of meeting minutes, which include information regarding admissions, finances, extracurricular issues, student and faculty life, alumni gifts and development, and issues pertaining to the operations and welfare of the school. The series also contains a small amount of correspondence.
  Arrangement note
  - Board of Trustees – Minutes, 1844-1850 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - David G. Cartwright correspondence, 1844-1875 (Box 506, Folder 9)
    General note
    Cartwright was a founder of the Brooklyn Female Academy
  - Board of Trustees – Minutes, 1850-1855 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Board of Trustees – Extracts from minutes, March 29, 1853 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Board of Trustees – Minutes, 1853-1874 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Board of Trustees – Minutes, 1859-1878 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Certificate of Abiel Abbot Law, Esq. Scholarship. Feb 1, 1865. Cancelled Nov 10, 1952, 1865, 1952 (Box 550, Folder -)
  - Board of Trustees – Minutes, 1874-1890 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Board of Trustees – Minutes, 1878-1901 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Alumnae Letter to Board of Trustees, 1883 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Board of Trustees Reports, 1886-1893 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Board of Trustees - Minutes and Correspondence, 1886-1941 (Box 158, Folder 8)
  - Board of Trustees – Minutes, 1890-1896 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Board of Trustees – Minutes, 1896-1902 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Letter from BT to Alumnae Association, 1896 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Letter from Alumnae Association to Board of Trustees, 1896 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Board of Trustees - Minutes, 1901-1920 (Box 506, Folder 10)
    Handwritten
  - Board of Trustees – Minutes, 1902-1908 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Board of Trustees – Minutes, 1908-1913 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Board of Trustees – Minutes, 1913-1917 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Board of Trustees – Minutes, 1917-1922 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Board of Trustees – Minutes, 1922-1929 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Board of Trustees – Minutes, 1929-1936 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Board of Trustees – Minutes, 1936-1942 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Board of Trustees meeting invitation to Mrs. Morrow, 1937 (Box 506, Folder 11)
  - Board of Trustees – Minutes, 1942-1943 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Board of Trustees – Minutes, 1943-1956 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Officers and Committee Members, 1946-1947 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Board of Trustees officers and committee members, 1946-1947 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Board of Trustees – Minutes, 1956-1970 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Scholarship information from Board of Trustees materials, 1968-1969 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Board of Trustees – Minutes, 1970-1975 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Letter to Parents from Board President regarding extension of co-education through eighth grade, 1972 (Box 506, Folder 12)
  - Board of Trustees – Minutes, 1975-1980 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - 1981 letter pulled from 1853 – 1874 minutes (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Board of Trustees – Minutes, 1980-1988 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Board of Trustees – Minutes, 1989-1993 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Board of Trustees – Minutes/Agendas, 1992-1993 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Board of Trustees - Minutes and other files, 1992-1993 (Box 506, Folder 13)
  - Board of Trustees - Marketing materials, 1993 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Board of Trustees – Minutes/Agendas, 1994 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Board of Trustees – Minutes/Agendas, 1995 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Board of Trustees – Minutes/Agendas, January – April, 1996 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Board of Trustees – Minutes/Agendas, June – November, 1996 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Board of Trustees – Minutes/Agendas, April – June, 1997 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Board of Trustees – Minutes/Agendas, September – November, 1997 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Board of Trustees – Minutes/Agendas, January 24, 1998 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Board of Trustees – Minutes/Agendas, February – September, 1998 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Board of Trustees – Minutes/Agendas, November, 1998 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Board of Trustees – Minutes/Agendas, January, 1999 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Board of Trustees – Minutes/Agendas, March – April, 1999 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Board of Trustees – Minutes/Agendas, June, 1999 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Board of Trustees – Minutes/Agendas, September – November, 1999 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Board of Trustees – Agenda/Minutes, January – May, 2000 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Board of Trustees – Minutes/Agendas, September, 2000 (Box 13, Folder 5)
- Series 3: Student administrative records, circa 1860-1979
  The series contains various student administrative records, dating from circa 1860 to 1979. These include reports of Scholarship and Promotion, academic transcripts, attendance and admission records, and Regents Examinations.
  The series is organized into six sub-series:
  Sub-series 3.1: Reports of Scholarship and Promotion
  Sub-series 3.2: Secondary and Junior College Transcripts
  Sub-series 3.3: Elementary Student Transcripts
  Sub-series 3.4: Transcripts and Report Cards (all grades)
  Sub-series 3.5: Attendence and Admission records
  Sub-series 3.6: Regents Examinations
  - Sub-series 3.1: Reports of Scholarship and Promotion, circa 1860-1979; 8.6 Cubic Feet in nineteen boxes
    The sub-series contains records of scholarship and promotion (or academic transcripts) of Packer Collegiate Institute students, dating from circa 1860 to 1979.
    It includes:
    Permanent Record of Promotions for 1869 and 1884; Semi-Quarterly Reports of Scholarship circa 1883-1898; Permanent Record: Semi-Quarterly Reports of Scholarship 1899-1911, vol. I-VIII.
    Two bound ledgers titled Permanent Record of Promotions, 1869 and 1884. Student transcripts including the year of promotion to each grade and graduation. Promotion dates circa 1860-1898.
    Sixteen bound ledgers titled Semi-Quarterly Reports of Scholarship, dated between 1883 and 1898. Student transcripts include student name, age, address, grade level and scholarship in various subjects. Arranged alphabetically by last name of student. Additional students are included in the index. Dates of admission, promotion, graduation or withdrawal are recorded as well as the school from which the student was admitted and the class to which he/she was assigned, and the college to which the student was admitted, if any.
    Eight bound ledgers titled Permanent Record: Semi-Quarterly Reports of Scholarship, 1899-1911, vol. I-VIII. Student transcripts with student name, age, address, department and grade. Arranged alphabetically by last name. Dates of admission, promotion, graduation or withdrawal are recorded, as well as the school from which the student was admitted and the class to which assigned, and college to which student was admitted, if any.
    Two bound ledgers and one folder documenting students entering college, dating from 1927-1979.
    - Permanent Record of Promotions, 1869 [academic transcripts], circa 1860-1898 (Box 35, Folder 1)
    - Permanent Record of Promotions, 1884 [academic transcripts], circa 1869-1898 (Box 35, Folder 2)
    - Semi – Quarterly Reports of Scholarship [academic transcripts], 1883-1884 (Box 36, Folder 1)
    - Semi – Quarterly Reports of Scholarship [academic transcripts], 1884-1885 (Box 36, Folder 2)
    - Semi – Quarterly Reports of Scholarship [academic transcripts], 1885-1886 (Box 37, Folder 1)
    - Semi – Quarterly Reports of Scholarship [academic transcripts], 1886-1887 (Box 37, Folder 2)
    - Semi – Quarterly Reports of Scholarship [academic transcripts], 1887-1888 (Box 38, Folder 1)
    - Semi – Quarterly Reports of Scholarship [academic transcripts], 1888 (Box 38, Folder 2)
    - Semi – Quarterly Reports of Scholarship [academic transcripts], 1889-1890 (Box 39, Folder 1)
    - Semi – Quarterly Reports of Scholarship [academic transcripts], 1890-1891 (Box 39, Folder 2)
    - Semi – Quarterly Reports of Scholarship [academic transcripts], 1891-1892 (Box 40, Folder 1)
    - Semi – Quarterly Reports of Scholarship [academic transcripts], 1892-1893 (Box 40, Folder 2)
    - Semi – Quarterly Reports of Scholarship [academic transcripts], 1893-1894 (Box 41, Folder 1)
    - Semi – Quarterly Reports of Scholarship [academic transcripts], 1895-1896 (Box 41, Folder 2)
    - Semi – Quarterly Reports of Scholarship [academic transcripts ledger], 1896-1897 (Box 552, Folder -)
    - Semi – Quarterly Reports of Scholarship [academic transcripts], 1897-1898 (Box 42, Folder 1)
    - Semi – Quarterly Reports of Scholarship [academic transcripts], 1898-1899 (Box 42, Folder 2)
    - Permanent Records: Semi – Quarterly Reports of Scholarship [academic transcripts], I (A – B), 1899-1911 (Box 43, Folder 1)
    - Permanent Records: Semi – Quarterly Reports of Scholarship [academic transcripts], II (C – E), 1899-1911 (Box 44, Folder 1)
    - Permanent Records: Semi – Quarterly Reports of Scholarship [academic transcripts], III (F – H), 1899-1911 (Box 45, Folder 1)
    - Permanent Records: Semi – Quarterly Reports of Scholarship [academic transcripts], IV (I – L), 1899-1911 (Box 46, Folder 1)
    - Permanent Records: Semi – Quarterly Reports of Scholarship [academic transcripts], V (M – O), 1899-1911 (Box 47, Folder 1)
    - Reports of Scholarship [academic transcripts], VI (P – R), 1899-1911 (Box 48, Folder 1)
    - Permanent Records: Semi – Quarterly Reports of Scholarship [academic transcripts], VII (S – V), 1899-1911 (Box 49, Folder 1)
    - Permanent Records: Semi – Quarterly Reports of Scholarship [academic transcripts], VIII (W – Z), 1899-1911 (Box 50, Folder 1)
    - Students entering college (two ledgers and one folder), 1927-1979 (Box 536, Folder -)
  - Sub-series 3.2: Secondary and Junior College Transcripts, 1922-1967; 5.5 Cubic Feet in eleven boxes
    Arranged alphabetically by surname. Loose photographs that were unidentifiable are filed at the beginning of the series.
    This sub-series contains the transcripts from the Packer Collegiate Institute Secondary School and Junior College, dating from 1922 to 1967. The transcripts include some or all of the following information: Student grades, dates entered and left Packer, date of birth, home address, parent's name(s), standardized test scores, extra-curricular activities, religious affiliation, and photographs. While most of the transcripts indicate if they are from either the Secondary School or the Junior College, there are some that remain ambiguous. There are records that contain information from both the Secondary School and the Junior College, and occasionally even Elementary School. Some transcripts show both maiden and married name if the student's status changed while attending the school. In most cases, the record is filed by maiden name. However, there are a few records where the maiden name was crossed out and replaced by the married name, in which case it is filed by the married name.
    - Miscellaneous Photos, 1922-1967 (Box 51, Folder 1)
    - Abberley – Adamowicz, 1922-1967 (Box 51, Folder 2)
    - Adler – Agee, 1922-1967 (Box 51, Folder 3)
    - Agnos – Aldino, 1922-1967 (Box 51, Folder 4)
    - Alexander – Alfke, 1922-1967 (Box 51, Folder 5)
    - Aliano – Allen, 1922-1967 (Box 51, Folder 6)
    - Allevspach – Amiqvet, 1922-1967 (Box 51, Folder 7)
    - Anastasio – Andersen, A., 1922-1967 (Box 51, Folder 8)
    - Anderson, B. – Anderson, R., 1922-1967 (Box 51, Folder 9)
    - Andrews – Angelo, 1922-1967 (Box 51, Folder 10)
    - Ansted – Antzis, 1922-1967 (Box 51, Folder 11)
    - Appel – Argenziano, 1922-1967 (Box 51, Folder 12)
    - Ariani – Arnold, 1922-1967 (Box 51, Folder 13)
    - Aronson – Asadorian, 1922-1967 (Box 51, Folder 14)
    - Aschenbach – Atherton, 1922-1967 (Box 51, Folder 15)
    - Atta – Auge, 1922-1967 (Box 51, Folder 16)
    - Aumuller – Austin, 1922-1967 (Box 51, Folder 17)
    - Avery – Awad, 1922-1967 (Box 51, Folder 18)
    - Ayoub – Azal, 1922-1967 (Box 51, Folder 19)
    - Baar – Babbott, 1922-1967 (Box 51, Folder 20)
    - Bachman – Bailey, 1922-1967 (Box 51, Folder 21)
    - Bainbridge – Baird, 1922-1967 (Box 51, Folder 22)
    - Baker – Balthis, 1922-1967 (Box 51, Folder 23)
    - Bandolin – Barbieri, 1922-1967 (Box 51, Folder 24)
    - Bard – Barney, 1922-1967 (Box 51, Folder 25)
    - Barr – Barrett, 1922-1967 (Box 51, Folder 26)
    - Barron – Barvc, 1922-1967 (Box 51, Folder 27)
    - Bassett – Baumgarten, 1922-1967 (Box 51, Folder 28)